Alright, so in this video then, we are
going to discuss project constraints.
Now constraint is a limiting factor on a
project.
Every project is bound by certain
constraints.
So as a very simple example,
let's say when you're building
a house, one of the major
constraints is cost, money.
You don't have unlimited
budget, I mean, the
average person does
not have unlimited budget.
You have to finish the project within a
certain amount of money.
money would be a constraint.
Say the project has a deadline.
You have to finish this project by this
date.
That deadline is a constraint.
Now traditionally there was, we used to
talk about triple constraints,
also known as a golden triangle or
sometimes referred to as the iron triangle.
And these three were traditionally known
as the triple constraints, right,
scope, time and cost.
These were traditionally known as triple
constraints.
And again, a constraint is a limiting
factor.
Your project is based on these
constraints.
And therefore, the way
the team operates are
going to be limited by these constraints.
Now, these are high-level constraints,
right?
But throughout the project, you are going
to be identifying detailed constraints.
So as a very, very simple example.
Let's say that we need to use this
machine.
There's a machine that we need to use in
order to do some work on our project.
And this machine is being shared by many
teams, right, different departments,
anybody in the organization,
you know, can select,
we can basically reserve
a time to use this machine.
So let's say this machine is available for
two hours a day, right?
Just for two hours a day, it's available
to us, right?
Let's say between the hours of 1 and 3 p
.m.
every day.
So now any activity that we perform,
that we need to perform that user that
machine, we now know that
we have to schedule those
activities based on the
availability of this machine.
So in this case, between one and three
every day.
So that time is a constraint on our
project.
The availability of that machine is a
constraint on our project.
So that is going to impact our schedule.
right so that the availability then is
going to impact our timeline is going to
impact our schedule right it's going to
impact when we perform the work how we
perform the work so a constraint is
basically anything that could either
impede or dictate the actions of the
project team right so in this case then we
have to perform the work if
we need to use that machine our
activity has to be based on
the availability of that machine.
Now, these triple constraints was the old
view, right?
The modern view is that there are many,
many constraints in the project,
not just three.
So this list of, you know, high-level
constraints has really been, you know,
the modern view is there's actually,
you know, it's been updated, if you like,
to six constraints that you get on every
project.
So we still have the original scope,
time and cost, right?
Scope, schedule, budget, instead of
schedule, or rather instead of time,
it could be called schedules,
so time and schedule are
the same thing, then budget
and cost are the same thing.
So these three are the
original triple constraints, but
in addition, we also have
resources, quality, and risk.
So these are six constraints that you
could get on every project.
However, there could be many, many more
constraints on a project.
So it's a very simple example.
Government regulations
is a major constraint on
many projects, but not
on every project, right?
And that's why it's not necessarily on
this list.
And any of the other constraints then is
going to have an impact, a potential
impact on scope, schedule, budget,
resources, quality, or risk.
Now, the way constraints behave with one
another, essentially a change in one
constraint could potentially lead to a
change in any of these other constraints.
So let's just take one as an example,
this one here, scope.
Senior management decides to increase the
scope of the project.
They have decided halfway through the
project to increase the scope of the project.
Well, you've got additional work to do.
There's additional scope, additional work.
So that's going to have an impact on your
schedule.
Because there's
additional work to do, that's
going to have an impact on your budget.
That will also have an impact on your
resources.
Equipment, supplies, labor, raw materials.
Your team members will need to be on the
project longer.
Right.
You might need to bring in some additional
team members.
You might need some more raw materials.
It's going to have an impact on machines.
You might need some more machines and
tools and so and so forth, which again is
going to have an impact of increasing your
budget.
Your increased work, right?
The scope has been increased.
That's going to have a direct impact on
equality management process.
Some of the testing that you've done,
for example, might need to be retested.
You've got additional work to do.
You need to create new test plans.
plans, new test cases, which might affect
some of the testing you've already done,
right?
That has an impact on your project.
And then based on this, you might be
identifying risks all over the place.
So a change in any of these constraints,
a change in one constraint could
potentially lead to a change in any of the
other constraints.
And these constraints are changing all the
time.
They're constantly changing.
Right, your schedule is changing,
you may be going ahead of schedule,
behind schedule, You may
be going over budget, under
budget, your resources
may be coming and going.
All of a sudden, one of your raw materials
may suddenly become a scarce raw material.
So now that might have an impact on your
schedule on your budget, which might have
a direct impact on your scope and the
quality of the work.
So again, a change in one constraint could
lead to a change in another.
Let's say you've identified a major,
major risk on your project.
Again, that could impact any of these
other areas.
How you handle these constraints is going
to determine success and failures of the
project, whether or not the customer or
the stakeholder is satisfied or not.
It can determine customer satisfaction.
And as a project manager,
you need to be able
to adjust to all of these
changing constraints.
Now, where are constraints documented?
Well, high-level constraints
generally are going to be documented
in the project chart, but
all the detailed constraints.
Remember, there are many,
many constraints on a project
you're going to be identifying
throughout your project.
The example I just gave was availability
of one machine.
That is a constraint on the project.
Where would those be documented?
Where would that be documented?
Could be documented in the scope
statement.
It'd be documented in the assumption log.
A document called the assumption log.
So the assumption log then is documenting
all detailed assumptions and constraints.
So these were then of the major
constraints.
Remember, these are the six major
constraints that you get on every project,
scope, scheduled budget, resources,
quality and risk.
Remember, there could potentially be many,
many more constraints on a project.